A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Treasurer, Ledgers and Account Books FA866
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Corporation, Treasurer, Ledgers and Account Books
1910-1978
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA866
7 Cubic Feet 8 boxes and 6 packages. Extent is approximate.
8 boxes and 6 packages.
Scope and Contents
Consists of cash books, ledgers, journals, security account books, security ledgers, security logs, and vault records kept by the office of the treasurer of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research. The records were subsequently kept by the office of the controller (created in 1959).
Arrangement
Chronological or alphabetical order.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 190-4
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
By the By-Laws of the Corporation adopted in 1910, a Treasurer of the Corporation was to be elected by the Board of Trustees at the annual meeting. The Treasurer was designated as the officer to have custody of the permanent funds and securities of the Corporation, to pay bills incurred by resolution of the Board of Trustees under the authority of the Executive Committee, and to make payments to the Board of Scientific Directors upon authorized requisition from them. It was the duty of the Treasurer to keep proper books, to present at each meeting an exact accounting of receipts and disbursements and to present an annual report of the accounts of the year. Additions to the Rules of the Board of Trustees provided that the Treasurer act as secretary of. the Finance Committee and have custody, of its minutes and other papers and documents relating to the work of the committee.
The first treasurer of the Corporation was Louis Guerineau Myers who served until 1932. Costs of the Treasurer's office were shared among several of the Rockefeller philanthropic enterprises such as the General Education Fund and the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Fund. The Board of Trustees was empowered to appoint an Assistant Treasurer and Lefferts Mason Dashiell was appointed in 1923. He became Acting Treasurer in 1932 upon the death of Louis G. Myers and was appointed Treasurer of the Corporation in 1939. Edward Robinson became Assistant Treasurer and Treasurer in 1939 with Benson Blake as Assistant Treasurer. In 1942 Edward Emerson became Assistant Treasurer and in 1954 he was succeeded by Robert Letort.
In 1953 new By-Laws of the Corporation were adopted, and under the reorganization then instituted a complete study of the business and financial administration of the Institute was authorized. Over a period of several years thoroughgoing changes of positions and responsibilities were established.
Between 1955-1959 Edward Robinson served as Treasurer and Robert Letort as Assistant Treasurer. Lindsley F. Kimball became Treasurer April 1959 (though elected to take office January 1, 1959) and William E. Dietz took office as Assistant Treasurer in March 1959. The office of William Dietz was enlarged to include the newly created office of Comptroller which included supervision of the office of the Bursar which in 1961 became the Bursar and Deputy Assistant Treasurer.
In May 1965 when Lindsley F. Kimball retired, J. Richardson Dilworth, who as Trustee had been very active and influential on the Finance Committee became Treasurer. Until 1969, while new patterns were developing, William E. Dietz, as Assistant Treasurer and Controller supervised much of the financial management of the University. William E. Dietz retired December 1969.
Finally a clear-cut division between the management of the University's business and the management of financial properties and investments was established. Joseph Richardson Dilworth served as Treasurer, Sydney Anglin Woodd-Cahusac as Associate Treasurer and Arthur Francis Hubbard as Deputy Assistant Treasurer. In May 1971 J. Richardson Dilworth, who continued as a trustee of the University and chairman of its Finance Committee was succeeded as Treasurer by Sydney A. Woodd-Cahusac and in 1972 Arthur F. Hubbard became Assistant Treasurer.
- Inactive Investment Security Log A-B, 1910-1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Limited access. Consult Archivist.
- Inactive Investment Security Log C, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Inactive Investment Security Log D-F, 1952-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Inactive Investment Security Log G-K, 1946-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Inactive Investment Security Log L-P, 1936-1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Inactive Investment Security Log Q-T, 1929-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Inactive Investment Security Log U-Z, 1916-1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Inactive Securities Sheets A-I, 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Inactive Securities Sheets K-P, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Inactive Securities Sheets S, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Inactive Securities Sheets U-V, 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Journal No. 1, 1910-1936 (Box 2)
- Journal No. 2, 1936-1953 (Box 2)
- Journal No. 4, 1966-1970 (Box 3)
- Vault Record Book, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
- Vault Record Book, 1957-1959 (Box 3)
- Vault Record Book, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
- Cash Book No. 1, 1910-1926 (Box 4)
- Cash Book No. 2, 1926-1936 (Box 4)
- Cash Book No. 4, 1945-1953 (Box 5)
- Cash Book No. 5, 1953-1959 (Box 5)
- Cash Book No. 6, 1959-1962 (Box 6)
- Cash Book No. 7, 1962-1965 (Box 6)
- Cash Book No. 8, 1965-1967 (Box 7)
- Ledger No. 1, 1911-1916 (Box 7)
- Securities No. 3 [Stocks], 1959-1975 (Box 8)
- Securities Ledger, 1974-1978 (Box 8)
- Securities No. 1 [Bonds, Trusts, and Gifts], 1930-1959; 1; package (Package 1)
- Securities No. 2 [Stocks and Mortgages], 1916-1956; 2; package (Package 2)
- Securities Ledger, 1911-1929; 3; package (Package 3)
- Securities Ledger No. 5 [Stocks and Bonds], 1955-1959; 4; package (Package 4)
- Ledger No. 2, 1917-1926; 5; package (Package 5)
- Ledger No. 5, 1945-1956; 6; package (Package 6)